In the last segment, we saw two active
attacks that can completely destroy the
上一节我们看了两个可以完全破坏CPA安全加密的安全性的主动攻击
security of CPA secure encryption. In this
segment, we're gonna define a new concept,
本节课我们将定义一个新概念
called authenticated encryption, that
remains secure in the presence of an
叫做认证加密 即对主动攻击者也能保持安全
active adversary. In later segments, we'll
construct encryption schemes that satisfy
在后面几节 我们将组建满足这个认证加密新概念的加密机制
this new authenticated encryption concept.
So what is authenticated encryption?
那什么是认证加密呢？
Authenticated encryption is a cipher where
as usual the encryption algorithm takes a
认证加密是一个密码 通常是个加密算法
key, a message and optionally a nonce and outputs
a cipher text. The decryption algorithm as
取密钥 信息和一个可选择的临时值作为输入 输出一个密文
usual outputs a message. However, here the
decryption algorithm is allowed to output
解密算法通常输出一个信息 但是这个解密算法可以输出一个特殊符号
a special symbol called bottom. When the
decryption algorithm outputs the symbol
叫做⊥ 当解密算法输出符号⊥时
bottom, basically it says that the cipher
text is invalid and should be ignored. The
密文是无效的 而且应当被忽略
only requirement is that this bottom is
not in the message space so that in fact
唯一的要求是这个⊥不属于信息空间
it is a unique symbol that indicates that
the cipher text should be rejected. Now
那么⊥就是唯一一个表示密文应当被拒绝的符号
what does it mean for an authenticated
encryption system to be secure? Well the
那一个认证加密系统是安全的是什么概念呢
system has to satisfy two properties. The
first property is that it has to be
这个系统必须满足两个性质 第一个性质是
semantically secure under a chosen
plaintext attack just as before. But now
它必须像之前一样对选择明文攻击是语义安全的
there's a second property which says that
the system also has to satisfy what's
第二个性质是这个系统必须满足密文完整性
called cipher text integrity. What that
means is that even though the attacker
这意味着尽管攻击者
gets to see a number of cipher texts, it
should not be able to produce another
能看到一些密文 他也不能生成另一个能被正确解密的密文
cipher text that decrypts properly. In
other words, that decrypts to something
换句话说 密文会被解密成其他非符号⊥的东西
other than bottom. More precisely,
let's look at the ciphertext integrity game.
更精确地的说 让我们来看一下这个密文完整性游戏
So here, (E,D) is a cipher with message
space M. As usual, the challenger begins
这里（E,D）是一个信息空间M上的密码 通常挑战者开始时
by choosing a random key K. And
the adversary can submit messages of his
选择一个随机密钥K 攻击者可以提交他选择的信息
choice, and receive the encryptions of
those messages. So here, C1 is the
之后收到这些信息的加密
encryption of M1, where M1 was chosen by
the adversary. And the adversary can do
这里C1是由攻击者选择的M1的加密
this repeatedly. In other words, he
submits M2 and obtains the encryption of
攻击者可以反复执行这个操作 换句话说 攻击者提交M2并得到M2的加密结果  等等
M2, and so on and so forth. He submits
many more messages up until Mq and obtains
他提交更多的信息直到Mq为止
the encryption of all those messages. So
here the adversary obtained Q cipher texts
然后获得了所有这些信息的加密结果 那么攻击者获得了q个他选择的信息的密文
for messages of his choice. Then his goal
is to produce some new cipher text that's
他的目标是产生某个新的有效密文
valid. So we'll say that the adversary
wins the game if basically this new cipher
如果这个攻击者产生的新密文被正确地解密了
text that the adversary created decrypts
correctly, in other words decrypts to
换句话说被解密成了非符号⊥的东西
something other than bottom. And it's a
new cipher text. In other words, it's not
我们就说这个攻击者赢了 它是某个新密文
one of the cipher texts that was given to
the adversary as part of this chosen
换句话说 它不是选择明文攻击中给攻击者的密文之一
plaintext attack. And then as usual we
defined the adversary's advantage in the
在这个密文完整性游戏中我们通常
cipher text integrity game as the
probability that the challenger outputs
将攻击者的优势定义为挑战者在游戏最后输出1的概率
one at the end of the game and we'll say
that the cipher has cipher text integrity
如果事实上对所有的有效攻击者
if in fact for all efficient adversaries
the advantage in winning this game is
其赢得游戏的优势都是可忽略的
我们就说这个密码具有密文完整性
negligible. So now that we understand
what cipher text integrity is we can
现在知道了什么是密文完整性 我们就可以定义
define authenticated encryption and
basically we say that the cipher has
认证加密 如果一个密码在选择明文攻击下是语义安全的
authenticated encryption if as we said
it's semantically secure under a chosen
同时也具有密文完整性
plaintext attack and it also has cipher
text integrity. So just as a bad example,
那么我们就说这个密码有认证加密 举一个不好的例子
let me mention that CBC with a random IV
does not provide authenticated encryption
带随机IV的CBC是不能提供认证加密的
because it's very easy for the adversary
to win the cipher text integrity game.
因为这将使攻击者很容易赢得密文完整性游戏
The adversary simply submits a random cipher text
攻击者只用提交一个随机的密文
and since the decryption algorithm for
CBC encryption never outputs bottom,
又因为CBC的解密算法永远不会输出⊥
it always outputs some message,
the adversary just easily wins the game.
它总会输出一下信息 攻击者就很容易赢得游戏
Any old random cipher text will decrypt
to something other than bottom
任何旧的随机密文会被解密成某些不是⊥的东西
and therefore the adversary directly wins
the cipher-text integrity game. So this is just
所以攻击者直接赢得了密文完整性游戏 这只是一个
a trivial example of a CPA secure cipher that
does not provide authenticated encryption.
不提供认证加密的CPA安全密码的简单例子
So I wanna mention two implications of
authenticated encryption. The first I'll
我想说两点有关认证加密的含义 第一点
call authenticity, which means that,
basically, an attacker cannot fool the
真实性 这意味着一个攻击者不能够欺骗接收者Bob
recipient, Bob, into thinking that Alice
sent a certain message that she didn't
让他认为Alice发送了一条她根本没有发送的确定的信息
actually send. So let's see what I mean by
that. Well, here, the attacker basically
让我们看一下这是什么意思 攻击者与
gets to interact with Alice, and get her
to encrypt arbitrary messages of his
Alice取得联系 让Alice加密任意一条他所选择的信息
choice. So this is a chosen plain text
attack. And then the attacker's goal is to
这是一个选择明文攻击 攻击者的目标就是
produce some cipher text that was not
actually created by Alice. And because the
生成一些并不是由Alice创建的密文 又因为
attacker can't win the cipher text
integrity game, he can't do this. What
攻击者不能够赢得密文完整性的游戏 他就不能做到这一点
this means is, when Bob receives the
cipher text that decrypts correctly under
这就是说 当Bob收到由解密算法正确解密的密文时
the decryption algorithm, he knows that
the message must have come from someone
他知道这个消息一定来自于一个知道
who knows the secret key K. In particular,
if Alice is the only one who knows K, then
密钥K的人 尤其是如果Alice是唯一一个知道密钥K的人
he knows the cipher text really did come
from Alice, and it's not some modification
那么他就知道密文确实是来源于Alice 并不是攻击者发送的某些修改
that was sent by the attacker. Now the
only caveat to that is that authenticated
唯一的注意的是
encryption doesn't defend against replay
attacks. In particular, the attacker
加密认证并不能抵御重放攻击 尤其是当攻击者
could've intercepted some cipher text from
Alice to Bob. And could have replayed it
可以截取由Alice发给Bob的密文时 他可以将信息重放
and both cipher text would look valid to
Bob. So for example, Alice might send a
这使得两个信息对于Bob来说都是有效的 例如Alice可能发一条信息
message to Bob saying transfer $100 to
Charlie. Then Charlie could replay that
给Bob让他转100$给Charlie Charlie可以重放出这条信息
cipher text and as a result, Bob would
transfer another $100 to Charlie. So in
结果就是Bob再转100$给Charlie
fact, any encryption protocol has to
defend against replay attacks and this is
事实上 任何一个加密协议都必须抵御重放攻击
not something that's directly prevented by
authenticated encryption. And we'll come
而这是被认证加密直接避免的
back and talk about replay attacks in two
segments. The second implication of
接下来两节我们会回来讨论重放攻击 认证加密的第二个含义是
authenticated encryption is that it
defends against a very powerful type of
它能抵御十分强大的攻击者
adversary, namely an adversary that can
mount what's called a chosen cipher text
例如可以运用所谓选择密文攻击的攻击者
attack. We're going to talk about that
actually in the next segment.
我们将在下节来讨论这个